<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>machine burning</title><link href="http://hitnail.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://hitnail.net/feeds/music.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://hitnail.net/</id><updated>2017-11-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Livecoding #1</title><link href="http://hitnail.net/livecoding-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-11-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>gus</name></author><id>tag:hitnail.net,2017-11-15:livecoding-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Is there a purest form of digital electronic music, akin to what acapella singing or hand drumming are to &lt;em&gt;acoustic&lt;/em&gt; music?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="https://www.mixcloud.com/beise/livecoding-1-20171110-almeida-centro-de-inspira%C3%A7%C3%A3o/" src="https://thumbnailer.mixcloud.com/unsafe/600x600/extaudio/7/4/4/5/3ccb-9b8f-41e2-976c-459d15f0eb60" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always been a fan of all-synthesized aesthetics, a lot of which is reflected in my own music production (check out my &lt;a href="https://beise.bandcamp.com"&gt;stuff on bandcamp&lt;/a&gt;, but , Boiling down digital electronic music to its essence, free from the sound and UX design biases of Ableton, Native Instruments et al., tempted me a lot -- specially being a programmer -- and required lower level tools and more powerful abstractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I started reading into the basics of audio design and synthesis, and eventually found exactly what I've been looking for with &lt;a href="https://supercollider.github.io"&gt;SuperCollider&lt;/a&gt;: code  meets concert, science meets art, algorithm meet music. And all of that is GPL open source!
From the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SuperCollider"&gt;wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; itself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an efficient and expressive dynamic programming language providing a framework for acoustic research, algorithmic music, interactive programming and live coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting to grips with the language and techniques used in programming has been a very pleasant ride, with the help of the folks at the &lt;a href="https://toplap.org/"&gt;TOPLAP&lt;/a&gt; community and the many helpful learning resources (which will be the subject of a future blog post).
Actually, there's even an existing &lt;a href="https://algorave.com/"&gt;Algorave&lt;/a&gt; movement, which is gaining more and more media attention lately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I've finally presented the first results of my research in livecoding in front of an audience at the &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/226940455"&gt;Almeida Centro de Inspiração&lt;/a&gt; in downtown Belo Horizonte.
Visuals were made by my friend &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/mdzubaart/?fref=ts"&gt;Zuba&lt;/a&gt;, and the reception of the totally non-geek audience to the 30 minute set was amazing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check it out at &lt;a href="https://www.mixcloud.com/beise/livecoding-1-20171110-almeida-centro-de-inspira%C3%A7%C3%A3o/"&gt;mixcloud&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="mixcloud"></category><category term="livecoding"></category><category term="supercollider"></category></entry><entry><title>Fuga de Berlim EP</title><link href="http://hitnail.net/fuga-de-berlim-ep.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-01-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>gus</name></author><id>tag:hitnail.net,2017-01-18:fuga-de-berlim-ep.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm pleased to announce (or document, as I don't expect anyone to read this) my &lt;em&gt;Fuga de Berlim&lt;/em&gt; EP.
It contains 4 tracks in various styles ranging from ambient, deep house influenced samba, a dark breed of electronica and some sort of tropical spoken word synth-folk. For those curious, the voice on the last track is an excerpt from an interview with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Baudrillard"&gt;Jean Baudrillard&lt;/a&gt;, where he's talking about his 2007 book &lt;a href="http://www2.ubishops.ca/baudrillardstudies/vol-8_1/v8-1-carnival.html"&gt;Carnival and Cannibal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen and download it at &lt;a href="https://beise.bandcamp.com/album/fuga-de-berlim"&gt;bandcamp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="https://beise.bandcamp.com/album/fuga-de-berlim" src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a2167604243_16.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="bandcamp"></category></entry></feed>