<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>machine burning</title><link href="http://hitnail.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://hitnail.net/feeds/music.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://hitnail.net/</id><updated>2018-02-03T00:00:00-02:00</updated><entry><title>Bandcamp onephrasers 2018-01</title><link href="http://hitnail.net/bandcamp-onephrasers-2018-01.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2018-02-03T00:00:00-02:00</updated><author><name>gus</name></author><id>tag:hitnail.net,2018-02-03:bandcamp-onephrasers-2018-01.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I really enjoy digging records on &lt;a href="http://bandcamp.com"&gt;bandcamp.com&lt;/a&gt;.
It's a music streaming and distribution service that cuts the middle man between artists and listeners. If you like the music, you can support the artist directly by buying a DRM-free digital copy. Couldn't be simpler than that.
The service also provides some ways for users to find new music, ranging from recommendations (at the bottom of the page) to blog articles about various styles (on &lt;em&gt;Bandcamp Daily&lt;/em&gt;), and the ability to &lt;em&gt;follow&lt;/em&gt; artists and then access an aggregated feed of releases.
What it doesn't provide is a playlist feature, nor some AI-driven infinite radio.
This seemingly crippling lack of feature makes the tool an oasis in a world of machine learning DJs: you have to choose your records again, just like you did before Spotify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kept find gems in this website, so I decided to publish a list of my favorite records released every month, describing them in one phrase.
Here is the first one, from January 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://miloraps.bandcamp.com/album/sovereign-nose-of-y-our-arrogant-face"&gt;scallops hotel - sovereign nose of (y)our arrogant face&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tags:&lt;/strong&gt; cloud-rap experimental-hip-hop spoken-word usa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Milo delivers jazzy lo-fi rap tunes filled with existentialist poetry and dreamy melancholic vibes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://jeffrosenstock.bandcamp.com/album/post"&gt;Jeff Rosenstock - POST&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tags:&lt;/strong&gt; indie-rock pop-punk usa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Captivating melodies, crisp riffs and tight production: really good 21st century punk music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://pwelverumandsun.bandcamp.com/album/now-only"&gt;Mount Eerie - Now Only&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tags:&lt;/strong&gt; singer-songwriter indie-folk avant-folk usa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too sad, too personal, too much talent, too eerie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://oddcoupleberlin.bandcamp.com/album/yada-yada"&gt;Odd Couple - Yada Yada&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tags:&lt;/strong&gt; psychedlic-rock garage-rock stoner-rock germany&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loads of energy, showing that pop-friendly stoner rock doesn't have to sound like the Queens of the Stone Age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://publicpossession.bandcamp.com/album/m-zaika-aqua-ep"&gt;Møzaika - Aqua&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tags:&lt;/strong&gt; house nu-disco kitschwave poland&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Close your eyes, you're in a pool party inside a Dreamcast game, everything is peaceful and crystalline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://sobomtl.bandcamp.com/album/self-service-digi"&gt;CFCF - Self Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tags:&lt;/strong&gt; house nu-disco canada&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elegant dance music, what Future-French-Touch would sound like if it was a thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://tysegall.bandcamp.com/album/freedoms-goblin"&gt;Ty Segall - Freedom Goblin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tags:&lt;/strong&gt; garage-rock folk-rock psych-pop usa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks all the gods for Ty Segall and all tasteful noisy psychedelia and pop weirdness he can gift us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://vacant.bandcamp.com/"&gt;Vacant - Origins&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tags:&lt;/strong&gt; future-garage chillstep uk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following Burial's path of darkness and grit -- and that's great, really.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Livecoding #1</title><link href="http://hitnail.net/livecoding-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-11-15T00:00:00-02:00</updated><author><name>gus</name></author><id>tag:hitnail.net,2017-11-15:livecoding-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Is there a purest form of digital electronic music, akin to what acapella singing or hand drumming are to &lt;em&gt;acoustic&lt;/em&gt; music?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="https://www.mixcloud.com/beise/livecoding-1-20171110-almeida-centro-de-inspira%C3%A7%C3%A3o/" src="https://thumbnailer.mixcloud.com/unsafe/600x600/extaudio/7/4/4/5/3ccb-9b8f-41e2-976c-459d15f0eb60" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always been a fan of all-synthesized aesthetics, a lot of which is reflected in my own music production (check out my &lt;a href="https://beise.bandcamp.com"&gt;stuff on bandcamp&lt;/a&gt; btw). Boiling down digital electronic music to its essence, free from the sound and UX design biases of Ableton, Native Instruments et al., tempted me a lot -- specially being a programmer -- and required lower level tools and more powerful abstractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I started reading into the basics of audio design and synthesis, and eventually found exactly what I've been looking for with &lt;a href="https://supercollider.github.io"&gt;SuperCollider&lt;/a&gt;: code meets concert, science meets art, algorithm meet music. And all of that is GPL open source!
From the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SuperCollider"&gt;wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; itself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an efficient and expressive dynamic programming language providing a framework for acoustic research, algorithmic music, interactive programming and live coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting to grips with the language and techniques used in music programming has been a very pleasant ride, with the help of the folks at the &lt;a href="https://toplap.org/"&gt;TOPLAP&lt;/a&gt; community and the many helpful learning resources (which will be the subject of a future blog post).
Actually, there's even an existing &lt;a href="https://algorave.com/"&gt;Algorave&lt;/a&gt; movement, which is gaining more and more media attention lately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I've finally presented the first results of my research in livecoding in front of an audience at the &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/226940455"&gt;Almeida Centro de Inspiração&lt;/a&gt; in downtown Belo Horizonte.
Visuals were made by my friend &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/mdzubaart/?fref=ts"&gt;Zuba&lt;/a&gt;, and the reception of the totally non-geek audience to the 30 minute set was amazing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check it out at &lt;a href="https://www.mixcloud.com/beise/livecoding-1-20171110-almeida-centro-de-inspira%C3%A7%C3%A3o/"&gt;mixcloud&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="mixcloud"></category><category term="livecoding"></category><category term="supercollider"></category></entry><entry><title>Fuga de Berlim EP</title><link href="http://hitnail.net/fuga-de-berlim-ep.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-01-18T00:00:00-02:00</updated><author><name>gus</name></author><id>tag:hitnail.net,2017-01-18:fuga-de-berlim-ep.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm pleased to announce (or document, as I don't expect anyone to read this) my &lt;em&gt;Fuga de Berlim&lt;/em&gt; EP.
It contains 4 tracks in various styles ranging from ambient, deep house influenced samba, a dark breed of electronica and some sort of tropical spoken word synth-folk. For those curious, the voice on the last track is an excerpt from an interview with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Baudrillard"&gt;Jean Baudrillard&lt;/a&gt;, where he's talking about his 2007 book &lt;a href="http://www2.ubishops.ca/baudrillardstudies/vol-8_1/v8-1-carnival.html"&gt;Carnival and Cannibal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen and download it at &lt;a href="https://beise.bandcamp.com/album/fuga-de-berlim"&gt;bandcamp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="https://beise.bandcamp.com/album/fuga-de-berlim" src="https://f4.bcbits.com/img/a2167604243_16.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="bandcamp"></category></entry></feed>